Guide to the Kathe Burkhart Papers MSS.467
Fales Library and Special Collections
Kathe Burkhart Papers
1908-2018
1985-2012
Fales Library and Special Collections
Burkhart, Kathe, 1958-
MSS.467
37.86 linear feet in 55 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 2 record cartons, 5 oversize flat boxes, 3 small flat boxes, one shared media box, and 1 flat-file folder.
168 Gigabytes in 5,402 computer files.
15 videocassettes (u-matic)
13 audiocassettes
1 sound cassettes (dat)
4 videocassettes (vhs)
5 film reels
1 videocassettes (minidv)
Kathe Burkhart (1958- ) is an American artist, writer, professor, and graphic designer based in both New York and The Netherlands. Her artwork utilizes various techniques including collage, painting, digital media, photography, video recordings, and sculpture. These techniques manifest in multiple forms including installations, short films, and writings. Her visual works frequently engage with themes such as gender roles, sexual politics, female dominance, and celebrity. The Kathe Burkhart Papers consist of paper and electronic files, and audio and video recordings on multiple formats which have been created and collected by Kathe Burkhart over the course of her personal and professional life dating from the 1960s to 2017. These materials document Burkhart's interdisciplinary work and provide contextual understanding of her artistic processes. Files and audiovisual material accumulated by Burkhart document her career as an artist through press clippings, artwork images, press releases, grant proposals, exhibition promotional material, and business correspondence. Datebooks and notebooks from the 1970s to the mid-2010s function as a combination of journals and appointment books. A significant amount of documentation is related to Burkhart's ongoing project, the The Liz Taylor Series, which originated in 1982, and includes source material, artwork images, clippings, and exhibition ephemera. Work files related to her writings include drafts, contracts, correspondence, and cover layouts, documenting her books From Under the 8-Ball (1985), The Double Standard (2002, 2005), Between the Lines (2006), and Dudes (2014). Burkhart's poetry, short stories, and articles are also in this collection. Files related to Burkhart's graphic design work and classes she taught at New York University and other institutions are also in this collection. Correspondence, writings, ephemera, and diaries related to Burkhart's Aunt Grace Knipe are in this collection and used as inspiration for her book Between the Lines (2006). Burkhart's personal files include photographs, astrology readings, correspondence, and high school and college ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Access to Series VIII. Journals, Datebooks, and Diaries (Boxes 47-66) is restricted to researchers until the donor is deceased.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kathe Burkhart in November, 2016; the accession number associated with this gift is 2017.004. Accretions to the collection were donated by Burkhart in February/April/May/September 2017, December 2018, and May 2023; the accession numbers associated with these accretions are 2017.010, 2017.085, 2018.080, 2018.123, 2018.125, and 2023.035.
Appraisal
During processing in 2021, two phonographic disc albums were identified with mold, and discarded.
2 vhs tapes, 11 CDs, and one audiocassette found to be commercial recordings were separated from the collection.
The following items did not fall within NYU's collection policy and were separated from the collection: books, 157 commercial phonographic disc albums, items of clothing (t-shirts, dresses, sweaters, shoes, leather jacket), slide light box, globe artwork, and other objects. A detailed list is available in the curatorial file for the collection. A syringe was disposed of as hazardous waste.
Arrangement
Organized chronologically within eight series:
Series I. Artwork
Series II. The Liz Taylor Series
Series III. Writing
Series IV. Graphic Design
Series V. Teaching
Series VI. Personal
Series VII. Grace Knipe Papers
Series VIII. Journals, Datebooks, and Diaries
Biographical Note
Kathe Burkhart (1958- ) is an American multi-disciplined artist, writer, professor, and graphic designer. Burkhart received her Bachelor of Fine Arts and Master of Fine Arts from the California Institute of Arts, Valencia. Her artwork utilizes various techniques including collage, painting, digital media, photography, video recordings, and sculpture. Her visual works have been exhibited both nationally and internationally, and frequently engage with themes such as gender roles, sexual politics, female dominance, and celebrity. The Liz Taylor Series, which Burkhart began in 1982, is one of her better known projects. Burkhart's writing takes multiple forms including novels, poetry, art reviews, and short stories. Burkhart has also taught courses in art, critical theory, and feminist theory at New York University and other institutions.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Kathe Burkhart Papers consist of materials created and collected by Kathe Burkhart in the course of her personal life and professional work as an interdisciplinary artist, writer, graphic designer and professor. Paper and electronic files in this collection contain original documentation which provides contextual understanding of Burkhart's artistic process dating from the 1960s to the mid-2010s.
Files related to Burkhart's career as a working artist include business correspondence; artwork images; grant application material; and exhibition files containing press releases, press reviews, mailers, and catalogs. Artworks and projects with a significant amount of material in the collection include The Authorized and Unauthorized Portraits; Torture Paintings; Nudes and The Abortion Project exhibition and related anthology book. A significant amount of material in this collection is specifically related to Burkhart's The Liz Taylor Series including artwork images, press clippings, exhibition installation images, and promotional material. Source material on the actress Elizabeth Taylor was accumulated over decades by Burkhart and dates from the 1960s to the mid-2010s. Burkhart began creating this series of works in the 1980s and continues as of 2021.
Labels, project descriptions, digital sound files, notes, final versions, and edited and unedited video clips related to her video projects are in this collection including Spendthrift, 1001 Coffee Shops, Nicole, Shave, American Woman, and Fugue. Burkhart's collection of studio diaries, notebooks, journals, appointment books, and desk calendars document her personal relationships; artwork ideas and writings; and daily activities while living and working in both New York and Amsterdam from the 1980s to the 2010s. Because of the private nature of these journals, they are not presently available to researchers.
Burkhart's poetry, short stories, novels, and critical review work files include drafts, page design layouts, correspondence, and audio and video recordings of readings and spoken word performances. This collection also includes a selection of work samples and client files related to Burkhart's graphic design work. Burkhart has been a professor at New York University and other educational institutions, teaching courses in art and art theory including the courses Drawing I and II; Sex and Contemporary Visual Art; Art and Activism; and Introduction to Critical Theory. Teaching files typically include course descriptions, syllabi, reading lists, notes, and correspondence.
Material related to Burkhart's personal life includes magazine profile interviews; astrology charts and readings; photographs of Burkhart, friends, and pets; correspondence with family and friends; and ephemera from Burkhart's high school and college years dating from the 1970s and 1980s in West Virginia and California. Burkhart also collected material related to her aunt, Grace Knipe, including ephemera, letters, diaries, writings, and notebooks, which illustrate the life of a woman working and living in West Virginia during the 1920s to the 1950s. Burkhart used letters to Knipe from her friend, Kate Gibson, as inspiration for her 2006 novel Between the Lines.
Correspondence as well as artwork and personal images will overlap throughout all the series, because Burkhart's personal and professional lives are so interwoven.
Painters -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Feminism and art -- New York (State) -- New York.; Poems.; Short stories, American -- 20th century.; Art -- Exhibitions -- 20th century; Art -- Exhibitions -- 21st century.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Art, American -- 20th century; Digital images.; Video recordings.; Audiotapes.; Typescripts; Clippings (information artifacts); Diaries; Taylor, Elizabeth
- Series I. Artwork, 1965-2017; 11.25 Linear Feet in 11 manuscript boxes, 2 record cartons, 2 oversize flat boxes, and 1 flat-file folder.; 165.5 Gigabytes in 3,814 computer files.; 15 videocassettes (u-matic); 3 audiocassettes; 2 videocassettes (vhs); 1 videocassettes (minidv); 5 film reels
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material related to Burkhart's work as a multidisciplinary artist using techniques including painting, collage, drawing, art installations, photography, and filmmaking. Specific artworks and projects with a significant amount of material in this series include the The Abortion Project, Torture Paintings, Nudes, Numbers & Letters, and Still Life Series/Hard Core. Paper and electronic files contain sale invoices; loan agreements; exhibition installation images; artwork images; and exhibition promotional and planning files. Files related to Burkhart's Liz Taylor Series artworks are arranged into Series II, although Taylor Series material may be found throughout Series I, if it was listed or shown with other Burkhart artworks.
  Burkhart's creative process as it relates to her video projects is illustrated through both her paper and electronic file notes, project descriptions, and film stills, as well as video and sound recordings on various formats. Video projects with significant documentation in this series include Spendthrift, 1001 Coffee Shops, Nicole, Shave, American Woman, and Fugue. This series also contains a video recording, reviews, film stills, screening invitation, and project descriptions for "Performance, May May 26, 1995 Pascara, Italy," an art performance piece and the wedding ceremony for Burkhart and Jozef van Wissem. This project also included limited edition handcuffs which were produced to accompany this video piece, and this series contains handcuff descriptions, images, and documentation. Her correspondence files contain communications with gallery owners, fellow artists, exhibition curators, and art collectors.
  Funding files in this series contain correspondence, status and final reports, as well as application packets which often include project descriptions, artwork images, artist statements, and resumes. This type of funding opportunities made it possible for Burkhart to support herself as a writer and artist.
  From the 1980s to 2017, Burkhart lived part of the year in a live/work space in Brooklyn. This series contains the accumulation of files related to Burkart and other resident artists' decades-long conflict with her Brooklyn aprtment/studio building owners, due to poor maintenance of the building. Her documentation of unsafe living conditions and subsequent legal actions were collected in the form of correspondence photographs, and public court documents. This series also contains ad postings, correspondence, sublet agreements, conflict documentation, and apartment use instruction lists related to Burkhart subletting her apartment to various artists while living in Holland for a portion of the year.
  - Artwork Source Material, 1965-1992, undated; cuid36384 (Box 1, Folder 1-8, Box 28, Folder 1, Box 44)
  - "Home", May, 1980; cuid36451 (Box 46, Super 8mm film reel 467.0021)
  - Notated Video Editing Machine Manual, 1981; cuid36385 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit Promotional Material and Installation Documentation, 1981-2014; cuid36185 (Box 2, Folder 2-5, Box 28, Folder 3-4, Flat-file-folder 1, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_16)
  - "Freeway Tape -- Rough Cut, Video Only", 1982; cuid36386 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0033)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 15 minutes
  - "Window Dub", 1983-11-11; cuid36387 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0035)
  - "Home Movies / Loveland", December 1983; cuid36388 (Box 46, U-matic 467.0024)
  - Things I Do with Boys -- Survivors Tape Titles, circa 1983; cuid36389 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0031)
  - Things I Do with Boys -- Scene Titles, circa 1983; cuid36390 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0030)
  - Things I Do with Boys -- Scene Titles, circa 1983; cuid36391 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0034)
  - Things I Do with Boys and Lovechild -- Video Recording, circa 1983; cuid36186 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_79)
  - Things I Do with Boys -- Still Image, 2004; cuid36187 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_29)
  - Spendthrift -- Titles and Keys, 1984-05-04; cuid36188 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0029)
  - Spendthrift -- Reel 1, Master, circa 1985; cuid36392 (Box 46, U-matic 467.0025)
  - Spendthrift -- Reel 2, Master, circa 1985; cuid36393 (Box 46, U-matic 467.0026)
  - Spendthrift -- Reel 3, circa 1985; cuid36394 (Box 46, U-matic 467.0027)
  - Spendthrift -- Reel 4 -- Interviews -- Linda, Mary Anne, Julie, circa 1985; cuid36395 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0028)
  - Spendthrift -- Window Dub, circa 1985; cuid36396 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0036)
  - Spendthrift -- Video Recording, circa 1985; cuid36397 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_78)
  - Lovechild, 1983; cuid36398 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0032)
  - Lovechild -- Video File, circa 1983; cuid36189 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_77)
  - Survivors Video -- Title Layout Sheets, 1984; cuid36399 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Survivors -- Master, August 1988; cuid36400 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0037)
  - Brooklyn Apartment / Studio -- Notes, Legal Files, Documentation, 1985-2017; cuid36401 (Box 3, Folder 1-17)
  - Amsterdam and Brooklyn Apartments / Studios -- Images, Building Dispute Files, 1994-2013; cuid36190 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_6)
  - Grants and Funding, 1985-2017; cuid36191 (Box 4, Folder 1-9, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_18)
  - Film and Video Notes, 1986, undated; cuid36402 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1999; cuid36403 (Box 5, Folder 2-9, Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2003; cuid36192 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_15)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2017, undated; cuid36404 (Box 6, Folder 4-10)
  - Feature Gallery -- Hudson, 1988-1992; cuid36405 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Articles and Reviews, 1988-2014; cuid36193 (Box 7, Folder 2-3, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_7)
  - Flash Art -- Correspondence and Art Sale-Related, 1990-1991; cuid36406 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - White Columns Exhibition -- Letter, Form, Promotional Mailers, 1990-1994; cuid36407 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - The Abortion Project -- Anthology Book Files and Page Layout Boards, 1990-1992; cuid36408 (Box 7, Folder 6-12, Box 8, Folder 1-4, Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - The Abortion Project -- Exhibition Files and Design Layout Boards, 1990s; cuid36194 (Box 8, Folder 5-10, Box 9, Folder 1-4, Box 18, Folder 4, Box 44, Folder 2, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_4)
  - The Abortion Project -- Reading Event 1, 1990s; cuid36409 (Box 46, Audiocassette 467.0010)
  - The Abortion Project -- Reading Event 2, 1990s; cuid36410 (Box 46, Audiocassette 467.0011)
  - The Abortion Project -- T-shirt, 1990s (Box 67)
  - Playlist for the Painting Cum, 1991; cuid36411 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Art Exhibition -- Guest Book, 1991; cuid36412 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Speaker Project -- Compilation of Sound Works by Artists, 1992; cuid36413 (Box 46, Audiocassette 467.0004)
  - The Torture Paintings -- Artwork Statements and Images, circa 1992-2017; cuid36195 (Box 9, Folder 7, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_28)
  - Venice Biennale -- Price List, Insurance, Catalogue Information, 1993; cuid36414 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Consignment Agreements, Artwork and Price Lists, 1993-2014; cuid36196 (Box 9, Folder 9, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_9)
  - Artist Statements and Bios, 1994-2013, undated; cuid36197 (Box 11, Folder 9, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_8)
  - Artwork Donations and Invoices, 1994-2014; cuid36198 (Box 9, Folder 10, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_11)
  - Sketches, Drawings, Doodles, circa 1994, undated; cuid36415 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Performance, May 26, 1995 Pescara, Italy -- Burkhart and Jozef van Wissem Wedding -- Review and Video Still Images, cuid36416 (Box 9, Folder 12, Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Performance, May 26, 1995 Pescara, Italy -- Burkhart and Jozef van Wissem Wedding -- Project Description, Recording Files, Screening Invitation, and Accompanying Handcuff Artwork and Documentation, 1995-2013; cuid36199 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_24)
  - Performance, May 26, 1995 Pescara, Italy -- Burkhart and Jozef van Wissem Wedding -- Recording, 1996; cuid36417 (Box 46, Vhs 467.0017)
  - Performance, May 26, 1995 Pescara, Italy -- Burkhart and Jozef van Wissem Wedding -- Handcuff Artwork Image and Documentation, circa 1996-1997; cuid36418 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Photographs -- Unknown Group Visit to Burkhart Studio, 1995; cuid36419 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Designs, Sketches, and Images of Artwork, 1995, 2002-2014, undated; cuid36200 (Box 10, Folder 16, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_10)
  - Labels and Lists of Video Projects, 1995-2006; cuid36201 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_20)
  - The Book of Nights -- Sample Layout Pages and Documentation, circa 1996; cuid36420 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Artwork Damage Documentation, circa 1996; cuid36421 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Agreements and Contracts -- Exhibitions and Galleries, 1996-1997, 2001; cuid36422 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Groninger Museum -- Insurance Claim Case Documentation, 1997; cuid36423 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Shave -- First Cut, Master from Hi8, 1998; cuid36424 (Box 45, U-matic 467.0038)
  - Shave -- Video Still Image, circa 1998; cuid36425 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Shave -- Project Description, Film Stills, Clips, Recording Files, 2011-2013; cuid36202 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_27)
  - Burkhart Resumes, 1998, undated; cuid36203 (Box 10, Folder 3, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_26)
  - Collector Lists, 1999, 2005; cuid36204 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_14)
  - 1001 Coffee Shops -- Video Description, circa 1999; cuid36426 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - 1001 Coffee Shops, and Jozef van Wissem Concert Footage, circa 1999; cuid36427 (Box 46, Vhs 467.0015)
  - 1001 Coffee Shops -- Video Recording, circa 1999; cuid36205 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_76)
  - Drip Video -- Description, 2000; cuid36428 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Video Projects -- Recording Files, Still Images, Descriptions, 2000-2014; cuid36206 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_30)
  - Amsterdam / New Amsterdam - The Double Life Exhibition -- Work Files, 2000-2001; cuid36429 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Persephone -- Video Stills, Clips, Descriptions, and Recording Files, 2001-2003, 2010; cuid36207 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_25)
  - Notes, 2001, undated; cuid36430 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Installation Images, 2002; cuid36431 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Shipping Documentation -- Artwork from Belgium, 2002; cuid36432 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Art Installation -- Foam Letters, Chocolate Haiku Worksheets, Artist Statement, 2002, undated; cuid36433 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Slide Labels for Artworks (1982-2002), circa 2002; cuid36434 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Participant, Inc. -- Correspondence and Notes, 2002, 2005; cuid36435 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Jozef van Wissem Musical Albums -- Artwork Source Images, 2003-2005; cuid36436 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - The Authorized and Unauthorized Portraits Series -- Notebook, Releases, Images, and Artist's Statement, 2003-2007, undated; cuid36208 (Box 11, Folder 11, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_12)
  - Moti Hasson Gallery -- Correspondence and Notes, 2005; cuid36437 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Hard Core Series -- Images, 2005-2008; cuid36209 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_19)
  - Nudes Series -- Finished and Raw Images, 2006-2013, undated; cuid36210 (Box 11, Folder 10, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_22)
  - Name Tags and ID Cards, 2006-2017, undated; cuid36438 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - PS 1 and Mondriaan Fund Exhibition Documentation, 2007; cuid36439 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Exhibitions -- Art Shipping and Related, 2008-2015; cuid36440 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Nicole -- Video Clips and Still Images, 2010; cuid36211 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_21)
  - Fugue -- Video Stills, Recording Files, 2010-2011; cuid36212 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_17)
  - 2010-2011 Digital Photo Library Images -- Artworks, Exhibit Installations, Studio, Events, cuid36213 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_1)
  - 2012 Digital Photo Library Images -- Artworks, Exhibit Installations, Studio, Events, cuid36214 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_2)
  - 2013 Digital Photo Library Images -- Artworks, Exhibit Installations, Studio, Events, cuid36215 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_3)
  - Occupy Wall Street -- Video Clips and Thumbnails, 2011; cuid36216 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_23)
  - Cixous Lecture -- Video Thumbnails and Clips, 2011; cuid36217 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_13)
  - American Woman -- Video Stills, Recording Files, 2011-2013; cuid36218 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_467_ER_5)
  - Art Inventory Lists with Images (1980s-2014), circa 2014; cuid36441 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Momenta Art Project -- "Ask Me About Being…" Artists' Bumper Stickers, undated; cuid36442 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Mailing List, undated; cuid36443 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Amsterdam Studio Notes, undated; cuid36444 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Wet Pain Signs -- Artwork Sources, Copies, T-shirt, undated; cuid36445 (Box 11, Folder 7, Box 67)
  - Paper Fans -- "Truth", and One Covered with Stickers, undated (Box 68, Item 1-2)
  - Artwork Images within Publications, undated; cuid36446 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Exhibit Proposal and Description, undated; cuid36447 (Box 11, Folder 12)